Preliminary Guide to the Félix Martí-Ibáñez Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Félix Martí-Ibáñez papers
1935-1977
MS 1235
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
137.5
The papers consist of professional and personal correspondence, manuscripts, articles and essays, research materials, copies of his published works, administrative files of MD Publications and miscellaneous biographical and professional materials. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Martí-Ibáñez, Félix, 1915-1972
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Verna Sabelle, 1980, 1984.
Related Material
Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection, Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Scope and Contents
The Félix Martí-Ibáñez Papers date from 1935 until 1977 and consist of correspondence, writings, research and teaching material, lectures, photographs, audio tape recordings, and awards of Martí-Ibáñez. Also included are the administrative files of MD Publications.
Biographical / Historical
Félix Martí-Ibáñez (1915-1972): physician, editor; M.D., U. Madrid; general director of public health and social services, Catalonia, Spain, 1937, and then Undersecretary of Public Health and Social Services for Spain; director of wartime health education, Catalonia, 1937-1938; medical director Winthrop Products, Inc., N.Y., 1942-1946, and of E.R. Squibb & Sons, 1946-1950; founded MD Publications in 1950; professor and director of history of medicine department, NY Medical College-Flower Fifth Avenue Hospitals, NY.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Separated Materials
Correspondence from Josefina Martí de Barrera (sister of Martí-Ibáñez) was returned to the donor, June 2003.
MD; medical newsmagazine; Physicians -- Biography; Public health; Physicians; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Martí-Ibáñez, Félix, 1915-1972
- Inventory
  - Professional and personal correspondence and photographs of Doctor Martí-Ibáñez and news items on Doctor Martí-Ibáñez, 1941-1946 (Box 1–2)
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, Pre-1955 (Box 3–4)
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous, Pre-1955 and 1955 (Box 5–6)
  - Correspondence
    - A - Z, 1955-1956 (Box 7)
    - A - Z, 1957 (Box 8)
    - A - M, 1958 (Box 9)
    - N - Z, 1958 (Box 10)
    - A - B, 1959-1969 (Box 11)
    - C - E, 1959-1969 (Box 12)
    - F - H, 1959-1969 (Box 13)
    - I - L, 1959-1969 (Box 14)
    - M - O, 1959-1969 (Box 15)
    - P - R, 1959-1969 (Box 16)
    - R - S, 1959-1969 (Box 17)
    - S - Z, 1959-1969 (Box 18)
  - General Correspondence
    - A - Film (the Special correspondence for the same dates is in boxes 90-93), Through May, 1972 (Box 19)
    - Film - K, and miscellaneous Interoffice Memoranda (the Special correspondence for the same dates is in boxes 90-93), Through May, 1972 (Box 20)
    - L - R (the Special correspondence for the same dates is in boxes 90-93), Through May, 1972 (Box 21)
    - S - We (the Special correspondence for the same dates is in boxes 90-93), Through May, 1972 (Box 22)
    - Wo - Z (the Special correspondence for the same dates is in boxes 90-93), Through May, 1972 (Box 23)
  - MD General correspondence, MD of Canada Interoffice memoranda, MD (U.S.) Interoffice memoranda, 1957 (Box 24–25)
  - MD General correspondence
    - B - H, 1959-1965 (Box 26)
    - H - M, 1959-1965 (Box 27)
    - N - W, 1959-1965 (Box 28)
    - W - Z, 1959-1965 (Box 29)
  - MD of Canada General correspondence A - Z, 1959-1965 (Box 29)
  - Spanish correspondence
    - A - K, Through May, 1972 (Box 30)
    - L - Rodriguez, Through May, 1972 (Box 31)
    - Roeypal - Z, Through May, 1972 (Box 32)
  - MD en Español and MD Interoffice memoranda, Through 1963 (Box 33–34)
  - MD Interoffice memoranda, 1964 (Box 35–36)
  - Manuscripts and published volumes of De Noche Brilla El Sol (Vals), Viaje Alrededor De Mi Mismo, Las Pagodas, Waltz, Journey Around Myself, A Prelude to Medical History, and All The Wonders We Seek (Box 37–38)
  - Old manuscripts and notes on The History of Medicine, chapters I-IX (Spanish and English) (Box 39)
  - Old manuscripts and notes on The History of Medicine, chapters X-XIII (Spanish and English) (Box 40)
  - MD Editor's Essays
    - Manuscripts, 1957-1961 (Box 41)
    - Manuscripts, 1962-1963 (Box 42)
    - Manuscripts, 1964-1965 May (Box 43)
    - Manuscripts, 1965 June - 1966 June (Box 44)
    - Manuscripts, 1966 July - 1967 (Box 45)
    - Manuscripts, 1968-1969 (Box 46)
    - Manuscripts, 1970-1972 June (Box 47)
    - Manuscripts, 1972 July - 1973 (Box 48)
  - Manuscripts of All The Wonders We Seek: Thirteen Tales of Surprise and Prodigy, Los Buscadores De Sueños, and The Antibiotic Saga (coauthored by Henry Welch) (Box 49)
  - History of Medicine Lectures presented at the New York Medical College; manuscripts of the "History of Medicine" section for The Encyclopedia Americana, Fabrica de Medicina, and Fabric of Medicine (Box 50)
  - Fabric of Medicine: chapters I-V (Box 51)
  - Fabric of Medicine: chapters VI-XIII and chapters of The History of Medicine (in English and Spanish) (Box 52)
  - A Spaniard Abroad ( Un Español Por Esos Mundos ): manuscripts in English and Spanish, and miscellaneous manuscripts of novels and articles (Box 53–54)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts and book projects (Box 55)
  - Index to boxes 56-67 and essays and articles published in Latin American newspapers and magazines, 1945-1958 (Box 56–58)
  - Essays and articles published in Latin American newspapers and magazines, 1945-1958 (Box 59–61)
  - Essays and articles published in Latin American newspapers and magazines and various other manuscripts, 1945-1958 (Box 62–67)
  - Card catalogue of boxes 56 through 67 (Box 68)
  - Secondary research material
    - A - F (Box 69)
    - G - Hist (Box 70)
    - Hist - Med (Box 71–72)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 73–74)
    - O - Psychiatry (Box 75–76)
    - Sigerist - Spanish Med (Box 77)
    - Fin - H (Box 78)
    - He - Hist (Box 79)
    - Laín - Lulio (Box 80)
    - MacArthur - Mental Health (Box 81)
    - Mexico - Morocco (Box 82)
    - Motion Sickness - Pacific Isles (Box 83)
    - Parapsychology - Phillipine (Box 84)
    - Plague - Romanticism (Box 85)
    - Rusk - Space (Box 86)
    - Spain - Turkey (Box 87)
    - U - W (Box 88)
    - Women - Zumaya (Box 89)
  - Special correspondence (the General correspondence for the same dates is in boxes 19-23)
    - A - Brussel, Through May, 1972 (Box 90)
    - Burke - E, Through May, 1972 (Box 91)
    - F - Le, Through May, 1972 (Box 92)
    - Li - N, Through May, 1972 (Box 93)
    - O - Se, Through May, 1972 (Box 94)
    - Si - Z, Through May, 1972 (Box 95)
  - Correspondence with physicians and others in various countries A - Japan (miscellaneous), Through 1972 (Box 96)
  - Correspondence with physicians and others in various countries Japan (select) - U.S., Through 1972 (Box 97)
  - Correspondence with actors, actresses, directors, film scenarists, dramatists, and others in the performing arts, Through 1972 (Box 98)
  - Memoranda on MD concept; ideas; thank you notes from staff; notes and letters from staff; various messages to staff, 1957-1972 (Box 99)
  - Reviews of books written or edited by Martí-Ibáñez (Box 100)
  - MD Editor's Essays: manuscripts and outlines of television programs by Martí-Ibáñez, 1974-1975 (Box 101)
  - University diplomas and awards, eleven framed, nine unframed (Box 102–104)
  - Secondary research material: additional history and miscellaneous, English and Spanish (Box 105–106)
  - Tapes of lectures on the History of Medicine at New York Medical College, tapes to friends and MD staff, miscellaneous tapes (Box 107–109)
  - Reviews of books written or edited by Martí-Ibáñez (Box 110)
  - Correspondence with writers A - Kersh (Box 111)
  - Correspondence with writers L - Maugham, S. (Box 112)
  - Correspondence with writers Mc - Z (Box 113)
  - Correspondence with family members (Box 114)
  - Biographical and autobiographical material; legal documents; birth and death cerificates; honors and awards; health; eulogies; obituaries; letters of condolence; handwriting analysis; letters of recommendation; articles on FMI; newsitems on FMI; Félix Martí Alpera (father of Félix Martí-Ibáñez): general information, manuscript by Martí Alpera (Box 115–116)
  - Poster of Félix Martí-Ibáñez, n.y. March 7 (Box 117)
    Scope and Contents
    Poster, circa 1930s, approximately 39'' x 25'', has photograph of Félix Martí-Ibáñez and advertises "Conferencia es la séptima del ciclo organizado por las Oficinas de Propaganda C.N.T.-F.A.I."
  - Letters of Josefina Martí de Barrera; Félix Martí-Ibáñez Album; honors and awards; film footage of William Somerset Maugham shot by Félix and Josephine Martí-Ibáñez at the Villa Mauresque, Cap Ferrat, the Riviera, France; two sets of recordings: "The World of Dr. Martí-Ibáñez," and "Through Time and Space With Dr. Martí-Ibáñez;" text of "The World of Dr. Martí-Ibáñez" (Box 118)
  - Correspondence with close associates and friends: Maline Asadorian, Betty Hamilton, John W. Hart, Douglas and Violita Macrae, Dr. Gregorio Maran ón, Aída Obler, Hernán Poza Juncal, Verna Sabelle(*), Frank Thompson, Antonia Ruiz Vilaplana, Dr. Alfonso Zamora Samper (Box 119)
    General note
    (*)The personal correspondence between Félix Martí-Ibáñez and Verna Sabelle will be turned in at a later date.
  - Partial bibliographies; bibliography of Spanish articles by Martí-Ibáñez in boxes 56-67; miscellaneous manuscripts, ideas, speeches, bookplates, projects for television and films; galleys of Waltz, etc. (Box 120)
  - Holographic notes, outlines, manuscripts, ideas (Box 121)
  - Travel, interoffice memoranda, various correspondence (most of the related correspondence is in the "General Correspondence" boxes or the "Special Correspondence" boxes) (Box 122)
  - Published articles and short stories by Martí-Ibáñez (Box 123–124)
  - Published articles and short stories by Martí-Ibáñez; reprints of FMI's Editor's Essays published in MD from September, 1971 to December, 1977 (these have not been published as a collection in book form); newspaper articles by Martí-Ibáñez, 1971 September - 1977 December (Box 125)
  - Various conferences, including the X Congreso International de Historia de la Medicina, held in Toledo Spain, 1935; New York Medical College material (Box 126)
  - Books by Félix Martí-Ibáñez (Box 127–129)
    - Fiction
      - All The Wonders We Seek: Thirteen Tales of Surprise and Prodigy
      - Waltz and other Stories
      - Los Buscadores de Sueños (Short Stories, Spanish)
      - De Noche Brilla el Sol (Short Stories, Spanish)
      - Las Pagodas (Novel, Spanish)
    - Nonfiction
      - The Mirror of Souls and Other Essays
      - To Be A Doctor, The Young Princes, The Race and The Winner
      - The Ship in the Bottle and Other Essays
      - Journey Around Myself: Impressions and Tales of Travels Around the World--Japan, Hong Kong, Macao, Bangkok, Angkor, Lebanon
      - The Crystal Arrow: Essays on Literature, Travel, Art, Love, and The History of Medicine
      - Centaur: Essays on The History of Medical Ideas
      - Ariel: Essays on The Arts and The History and Philosophy of Medicine
      - A Prelude to Medical History
      - Men, Molds, and History
      - The Pebble In The Bell
      - Books in The Physician's Life
      - The Antibiotic Saga (co-author)
      - Surco (Spanish)
      - Viaje Alrededor de Mi Mismo (Spanish)
      - La Flecha de Crystal (Spanish)
      - El Barco en La Botella (Spanish)
      - To Be A Doctor, The Young Princes; The Race and The Runner (Japanese)
      - A Prelude to Medical History (Japanese)
      - A Prelude to Medical History (Korean)
    - Editor and Contributor (FMI)
      - Tales of Philosophy
      - The Pageant of Medicine
      - The Patient's Progress
      - Henry E. Sigerist on The History of Medicine
      - History of American Medicine
      - The Impact of the Food and Drug Administration On Our Society
      - Antibiotics Annual, 1954-1955
      - Antibiotics Annual, 1955-1956
      - Antibiotics Annual, 1956-1957
      - Antibiotics Annual, 1957-1958
      - Antibiotics Annual, 1958-1959
      - Antibiotics Annual, 1959-1960
      - Antibiotic Therapy
      - Antibiotics in Nutrition
      - Antibiotic Therapy for Staphylococcal Diseases
      - Aureomycin
      - Polymyxin, Neomycin, Bacitracin
      - Assay Methods of Antibiotics
      - Symposium of Medicated Feeds
      - The Great Physiodynamic Therapies in Psychiatry
      - Psychiatry and Religion
      - Medicine and Writing
      - Health and Travel
      - Medical Writing
    - Contributor (FMI)
      - Terramycin
      - Erythromycin
      - Tetracycline
      - Symposia on New Facts and Perspectives of Broad-Spectrum Antibiotic Therapy. 1. "Oxytetracycline"
      - Symbology
      - Ecology of Human Disease
      - A Guide to Antibiotic Therapy
      - A History of Neurology
      - A History of Public Health
      - A History of Ophthalmology
      - The Best From Fantasy and Science Fiction
      - The Best From Fantasy and Science Fiction (paperback)
      - Never in This World
      - Terremicina (Spanish)
      - Terapia Antibiotica (Spanish)
      - Cuentos de España Hoy (Spanish)
      - Nuevos Datos y Perspecivas Sobre La Terramicina
    - Monographs (FMI) in Spanish
      - El Sentido de la Vida (Box 130)
      - España
      - Grandezas y Miserias de la Revolución Social Española
      - Higiene Sexual
      - La Canción Sin Palabras
      - Los Milagros Curativos en la Historia de la Medicina
      - Meditación del Mar
      - Mensajes a la Juventud Revolicionaria
      - Mensaje a México
      - Niños en Espaéa
      - Tres Mensajes a la Mujer
      - Consultoria Psíquico-Sexual
    - Books by FMI
      (Photostats. Hardcover editions not presently available)
      - Ensayo Sobre la Historia de la Psicología y Fisiología Místicas de la India (Spanish, nonfiction) (Box 130)
      - Obra (Spanish, nonfiction)
      - Aventura (Spanish, nonfiction)
      - Yo, Rebelde (Spanish, fiction)
    - Editor and Contributor (FMI)
      - The Adventure of Art
      - The Epic of Medicine
  - Reprints of essays by Martí-Ibáñez (Box 131)
  - Various tapes, secondary research material (Box 132)
  - Recording machine (Box 133)
  - Theatre, film and book reviews by Martí-Ibáñez, published in MD, 1957 January - 1972 July (Box 134)
  - Index:
    - A - Dentistry (Box 135A)
    - Depressants - K (Box 135B)
    - L - Q (Box 135C)
    - R - Z (Box 135D)
  - MD of Canada Editorial Board and El Medico, and miscellaneous unidentified files (Box 136)
  - Slides for the teaching of The History of Medicine, undated (Box 137A–137D)
  - Fantasists on Fantasy, ed. Robert H. Boyer and Kenneth J. Zahorski, with FMI's "Tell Me a Story,", 1984 (Box 138)
    Received from: Verna Sabelle, 1984 May 21